Zarana M Trivedi

SUMMARY

MBA with 11 + years of strong experience in Handling all functions including overseas customer correspondence, Custom compliance, International transport, Export Dispatches and Import shipments. Expertise in Handling export Dispatches & Documentation, Freight Forwarder Coordination, Freight Negotiation and Custom & DGFT Coordination.

SKILLS

Handling all Pharma General Cargo, Narcotics, Physcotropics, Temperature Control Inbound and out bound shipment using both ocean as well as Air Transportation, Freight Forwarder Coordination, Freight Negotiation, MIS Reports etc.

EXPERIENCE

Assistant Manager – Export Operations
Rusan Pharma Ltd | October 2015 – Present
Mumbai MH

Roles & Responsibilities:

- ✓ Manage Export operations of volume of 550 TEUs per Year by Sea & By Air.
- ✓ Ensure that lean process management implemented from receipt of order from customer till Delivery of Goods to Customer
- ✓ Liasoning with Customs, Port, carrier, Airline, CBN, SGS for smooth direct port delivery
- ✓ Applying for Narcotic & Psychotropic permissions for all the narcotic shipments at CBN Department and arranging Prof of Export Documentation submission.
- ✓ Lead team to manage all export related activities for Rusan handling Pre/post shipment formality with Export benefits such as advance licensing, duty drawback, MEIS, Export Under Restricted license, etc.

Rewards and Recognition

- ✓ Rising Young and Dynamic Star with Special Bonus of the Financial Year 2019-2020
- ✓ Best Employee of the year award, (Shining Stars of the Financial Year 2020 -2021) with Onetime Special Bonus announced in Annual General Meeting.
- ✓ Pole Star Award for outstanding performance, (Pole Stars of the Financial Year 2021-2022) with Onetime Special Bonus announced in Annual General Meeting.

Exim Manager – Export –Import Operations SMB Corporation of India | August'12 - September 15 Mumbai, MH

Roles & Responsibilities:

Import

- ✓ Co-ordination with supplier for getting material status of the shipments, giving the vessel schedule, status of shipping documents and other communication
- ✓ Co-ordination with Freight Forwarder, Shipping Lines for negotiates the Freight rates and other communication
- ✓ Co-ordination with CHA for clearance goods from customs
- ✓ Preparing MIS report and update to time to time
- ✓ Arranging Local Transportation from Port to Factory.
- ✓ Handling High Seas Sale Documents & Clearance.

Export

- ✓ Co-ordinate with Transporter, Freight Forwarder and Shipping Companies for negotiation the freight rates and other communication.
- ✓ Co-ordinate with buyer and getting the approval for shipping documents
- ✓ Co-ordinate with CHA for clearing the goods from customs
- ✓ Preparing MIS report and daily report and same send to management on time to time.
- ✓ Preparation & Checking of Pre –shipment and Post -shipment documents
- ✓ Responsible for checking of L/C's received from the buyers for the shipment so that the all shipment will timely dispatch.
- ✓ Arrange Liasoning with DGFT for Advance License, FPS License, FMS License, EPCG License, Status Holder Certificate (Export House, Star Export, Trading House and other's) and etc.
- ✓ Arranging Membership's with Different Government Agencies Like Export Promotion Council, FIEO, Pharmexcil, FDA.etc

Sr. Executive – Export-Import Operation Vishakha Polyfab Pvt. Ltd | Sept' 2010 – June '2011 Ahmedabad

Roles & Responsibilities:

- ✓ Negotiation & finalization of Freight
- ✓ Handling of Import documents like Invoice, Packing list, Bill of Lading/AWB, Certificate of Insurance, Certificate of analysis, MSDS & Tracking consignment status
- ✓ Co-ordination with CHA for clearing Import consignments under bond or direct delivery.
- ✓ Calculation and preparation of Custom Duty request for clearing Import consignment.
- ✓ Co-ordination with site supervisor for loading & unloading.
- ✓ Import cargo clear
- ✓ To maintain Import & Export expanses sheet and try to reduce cost in every month.
- ✓ Accounting DEPB utilization and maintain record in Excel sheet.
- ✓ Co-ordination with Supplier SCM team for Advance documentation.
- ✓ Submit Triplicate Exchange Control Copy to Bank with covering letter.
- ✓ To Prepare Bank Realization Certificate and proof of export documents
- ✓ Ensure smooth and efficient Exports in co-ordination with Business, Marketing, Purchase, Manufacturing, Operations, CSR teams and Overseas Customers.
- ✓ Co-ordinate with production sites for smooth functioning of stuffing the Cargo.
- ✓ Ensure proper Export Documentation Pre and Post Shipment (with L/C, without L/C, advance payment).
- ✓ Updating of Export Realization.
- ✓ To prepare all documents related to rebate of Excise Duty.

EDUCATION

- o MBA in International Marketing & Supply chain Sikkim Manipal University Ahmedabad -2009
- BBA (Bachelor of Business Administration) Saurashtra University 2006
- H.S.C. Gujarat Higher Secondary Education Board (2003)